hey everyone welcome again to another
interesting Tosca lesson
in today's session I am going to talk
about the new Tosca 16 features now
recently a couple of weeks back Tosca
released its latest version which is
16.0 and along with it came some
interesting features uh which are new
and some improvements so we are going to
talk about few of them not all of them
if you want to go to or the list of all
the features released in Tosca 16 you
can go to the blog introducing new
features in tosca16 and there you will
find the list of all the different
features which were released in this
version
now out of all these different features
which includes the try centers Mobile
agent for seamless connectivity for
Android and iOS
some of the important features which I
would like to pick it up and explain it
to you because I find it quite
interesting and also quite useful if you
are working in these applications right
so we are going to talk about uh
enhanced test automation for Oracle and
how Tosca has introduced the new Tosca
ID mapper along with the support for
Arya framework which helps you to build
your automation for Oracle Enterprise
applications
so we're going to talk about that these
two features in particular
and then we are also going to look at
the new UI like it's little different uh
Tosca 16 compared to all the previous
versions uh there is a new uh theme
which you can Implement a dark theme
along with some other themes which are
quite
um intuitive in terms of UI so we'll see
how it looks like in this particular
session
there is also Cloud license supporting
uh it's mostly for Tosca admins and then
we'll also
talk briefly about this test is
pre-execution approval which is quite
interesting if you are looking for
getting an automated flow of of approval
of your test cases before
um you go ahead and execute this test
cases right so that is an automation
flow through which you can
uh the Quest for approval for your test
cases and also a group can basically
review and approve your test cases
before these go into the execution so
it's a very interesting feature I will
talk about it and there are some other
enhancements like improvements to file
service
um some sap Innovations uh q-test
integration Dex enhancements uh
improvements to PDF automation
um very interesting if you are working
with the PDF comparison uh that is the
Mainframe improvements and also support
for Java 17 applications and then
um
support for the latest windows 11. okay
so all of these are different
enhancements and features which have
been released in Tosca 16. if you want
to go through the whole list and details
you can always hop uh into this link and
go through the details right but I'm
going to focus on few of these features
which I think is important and also
useful if you are working in these
Enterprise applications
and overall posca 16. so now let's get
started with our first topic which is
enhance test automation for Oracle
now if you have been working with Oracle
applications you know automated testing
is quite critical for ensuring um your
business processes are reliable but
Oracle implementations are quite highly
customized
and they are integrated uh with many
other systems which are under constant
change
so testing end to end is quite crucial
but um Oracle apps they all have
um like any other Erp system contain uh
Dynamic controls which are sometimes
difficult to automate so with Tosca 16.0
now Tosca has introduced the Tosca ID
mapper and support for Arya framework so
that all the complex controls which are
found in the Oracle applications can be
identified easily and your automation
could be more stable
so talking more about this ID mapper
right so with the Tosca new ID mapper
now we can select our own application on
this test uniquely identify controls by
adjusting the properties and then save
all the default IDs in a particular
Library which we can use for future use
or if some um someone else wants to use
this particular Library they can also
use it for other applications
so it is a comprehensive way to identify
various control types
and also
also it lowers your efforts in terms of
test customization and it also increases
stability
so now let's head back to our Tosca 16.0
uh Costco Commander and there we will
look at how the new ID mapper
functionality looks like how you can use
it to implement different automation for
your Oracle applications
and how it is helpful in terms of
identifying controls uniquely across
your Erp systems
so now I have opened my Tosca 16.0 uh
which is the latest version of Tosca now
it's quite easy to upgrade or if you are
installing a Tosca 16 as a completely
new version in one of your Windows
server or machine
you just need to download uh the latest
version of Tosca 16. from Dodge Center
support portal where you have created an
account and you have got a trial or a
full license you can just download it
and just go through the installation
it's pretty simple and straightforward
so I'm not going to spend time on
showing you how to install or upgrade
the Tosca version which you are
currently on or you are trying to
install a completely new version
now just to make sure that I am on the
right version I can also go to my about
Tosca and check whether this is the
latest Tosca 16.0
so which it is right so the version is
16.0
um and you can already notice there are
some UI changes but we'll talk about it
later
for now uh let's concentrate on our
um enhanced test automation for Oracle
applications including the Tosca ID
mapper right so for this um I have
already logged in into one of the
Oracle Erp application
and here we are going to look at how we
can use the Tosca ID mapper in order to
uniquely identify controls in this
particular application right so for this
particular purpose
um let's go to create a new contact okay
and once we reach this page we'll see
different controls
um which are Oracle based and which are
pretty dynamic in nature if you look at
their IDs they are all Dynamic IDs okay
so as you can see uh on this page there
are a couple of control types like text
boxes drop downs
um
and buttons right so there are different
types of controls present on this
particular page
so let's go back to our Tosca and here
inside modules let's create a new
folder so that we can scan this
particular application okay so here I'm
going to create a
a folder called ARP cloud
okay and inside this let's go ahead and
scan this application
okay um so once the application is
identified just select the application
and click on scan so that it starts or
the xcan window appears with all the
different controls which you want to
scan for this particular application
so
we'll go to the advanced tab once uh all
the controls are loaded in this
particular scan window
okay so let's go back to the advanced
window and here we can view all the
controls which are present for this
particular page right now if you have
worked previously in Tosca most of the
things on this particular screen would
look same we have different controls we
have different properties through which
these controls are identified but what
Tosca has done in addition to this is
for the Oracle applications
um now they have got a settings icon
here right and in this settings icon you
will see different options here we'll
talk about the Aria controls you can
turn on and off this Aria controls okay
uh but we
but let's focus on the
Tosca ID mapper and for that you need to
go to the unique application identifieds
section okay so here we can create our
own application identifiers
through which we can Define default IDs
for controls in a particular application
right so for this Oracle application we
can have our own default IDs for all the
controls so that they can be uniquely
identified using these default IDs okay
so for this what we have to do is uh we
have to Define our application name so
for here uh I will put Oracle okay
and you will see uh the application
identifier is by default it is selected
as title you also have an option for URL
and the value is
um automatically
created for this particular page okay
so now this is a unique application
identifier which is specific for a
specific application which you have
defined on your own right and now let's
go ahead and save this
okay so once you save this uh it is
going to save these default IDs okay and
then I will look at one of the controls
uh say for example First theme which is
a text box right so let's close this
window
and let's come here and here we will see
the different controls so we want this
uh first name which is a text box we
want to select this okay
so
once you select this
um all the properties would start
appearing here okay and you will see
that it has selected or it has scanned
this control and it is able to identify
using ID and some tag value
but the problem with the ID is as you
can see it is pretty Dynamic right so
you cannot basically depend on this ID
which looks uh pretty Dynamic and it can
change anytime okay so what we'll do
we'll deselect this ID and instead of
that what we'll select is we'll have a
default name which is first name and
then we will also select the visible
property which is true okay so these are
the two properties through which we want
to identify this control and the other
thing which we want to do is
we want to define a default ID on the
application Level for this control right
so this is the Tosca ID mapper it Maps
your IDs with your controls okay so now
we can Define our own default ID at an
application Level so as you can see here
once you select that option it comes as
select application so choose from
previously configured applications where
you want to save the default Define
default IDs okay
ah and here we can select our
application which we have created
earlier in the settings so here you will
see uh there is an option called Oracle
which we have created earlier okay so
select that and click on Save and now
the control would be reloaded right and
you will see that it has got now a
default ID at an application Level and
it has it will always select based on
these two properties okay
now the other good thing about this is
It's Not only applicable for this
particular control but for all the other
controls on this application like if I
go to last name
okay and you will see by default it has
selected the default name and visible
property but if I would have not given a
ID mapper or I would not have selected
the ID mapper then it would have
probably selected based on the ID and
tag right but since we have defined
um default ID at application Level so
all the controls in this application
will have this default ID through which
it can uniquely identify all these
controls right
so
this is how the Tosca ID mapper works
you need to go to the settings icon
which is a new icon on the xcan window
and you can Define your own application
name with a value
uh and then you can save it and then you
can go to the control and you can select
that particular value or that
application ID which you have created
and you can select it for all your
controls in the application this way uh
it will be uh more stable and you don't
need to customize it for every control
it will be automatically customized for
all the controls in your application so
um your customization times goes down
and you can focus more on the automation
rather than spending time on customizing
each and every control in the Erp
application
now let's talk about the next feature
which is available in enhanced test
automation for Oracle in Tosca 16.0
which is the support for Aria framework
but before that let's understand a
little bit about what is Arya and Arya
stands for accessible Rich internet
applications it is a framework that
makes it easy for users with
disabilities to view interact or access
web content and applications
it is used by assistive Technologies
like screen readers magnifiers or
text-to-speech
and Arya can be implemented across any
mobile web or Enterprise application
like Oracle workday Microsoft Dynamics
365 sap and others
now why this is important is because
Aria framework is going to be more and
more used across all the applications
all the controls are going to be built
using the Aria framework to help uh
users with disabilities to interact with
these applications more easily and this
is being regulated by the European Union
which is soon going to make it mandatory
for most of the applications to have
this area framework implemented uh in
their applications by 2025.
so in Tosca 16.0 it provides you with
inbuilt capabilities to automate this
controls with Aria labels it decides
based on the steering parameter if the
native area support should be considered
or not
so now let's see how you can use this
feature which is the support for Aria
framework in applications like Oracle to
identify controls based on this
particular feature
so let's go back to our Erp application
and let's go to some other page to view
some controls which we can
link with the Aria framework
so I'm going to go to a page and add a
absence here from the ARP application
and that will that will take me to this
page where um I can select a value for
my leave type
and then I can proceed right
but the thing to note here is these
three buttons now these three buttons
um are built with the Aria framework and
how I can tell that is
let's add another module for this
particular page
so let's scan the application
now we can select the application and
click on scan
so once the advanced view is displaying
all the controls again
um the new settings icon which we
already talked about so click on that
and then it will open a settings uh
window where you can find general
settings in general settings there is an
option to either ignore or enable the
Aria controls right
so by default this option would not be
checked out that means uh the Aria
controls would be taken into
consideration by Tosca but if you want
uh to ignore area controls you can
select this and click on Save and that
should uh basically turn off this
feature which means all your controls
would now be normally identified by the
properties right but uh since we want to
see how we can identify our controls
using the new Aria framework support
provided by Tosca 16 so let's check this
out and click on Save
and then um just close the settings
dialog box right now let's shift our
Focus uh to the three controls uh which
are on the top of this page right so
which are the save and close submit and
cancel
now as you can see these three uh
controls or buttons are within a table
now if you have not enabled the Aria's
support provided by Tosca then these
three buttons should be mostly visible
like a div elements and div elements are
difficult to identify as you know since
there would be lot of developments and
there would not be any unique properties
through which you can identify them so
when you enable the Arias framework
support then these are displayed as
buttons and if I select one of these
buttons and
I go to one of its properties we can see
that this is a Aria framework control so
if you go to the adapter
um and you can see here it is showing up
as tricentice Dot
automation dot engines dot adapter
and Dot aria.aria button adapter right
so it is one of the Aria framework
buttons or controls through which Tosca
is able to identify this controls as a
specific buttons right if if it is not
if the support is not present or the
Aria framework is not supported then it
would be difficult to identify these
controls on the application
so I can select all these uh three
buttons uh using the audio framework
support and I can save it to my module
and close this
um particular X scan
to have my module ready and now I can
work out with these three controls
right
so uh this is how you can turn on and
turn off the audio framework support if
you are working with a specific Aria
controls it's best to have that enabled
so that you can easily identify those
controls and start working on the
automation of your application
foreign
of Tosca as you can see uh the buttons
or the folders are little different uh
compared to the previous versions
um they have changed the folder icons
little bit the colors have changed the
overall UI looks little different right
and they have also introduced a few
other themes apart from the default
theme now personally I really like this
theme I've been working it's little uh
dark right now but I personally prefer
the default theme but if you go on the
top you will see this window and right
now I am on the light theme
and there are other high contrast light
and high contrast dark and also the
popular Dark theme now if you are used
to uh working on dark themes especially
on different IDs this could be ideal for
you uh
to get the stock theme enabled for your
uh Tosca 16.0
so you can always change back your theme
to The Light default theme
which is my personal favorite
so uh that's that's a new feature a new
theme which has been um introduced in
Tosca 16.0 and it provides you with a
different UI layout uh which is better
for different uh users depending on your
personal choices and
um how you are used to working with
different automation tools or IDs
now talking about the final feature in
this particular session so the test case
is pre-execution approval which is an
automated process uh being introduced in
Tosca 16.0
now let's talk about it uh what it is
and how does it work
so Tosca pre-execution approval uh as I
said it's an automated process to
request and Grant approval for your test
cases
it allows us to validate our test cases
before they are run
so that
um the test cases are all validated and
no unauthorized modifications can be
done on this test cases if they are once
validated and approved
the approval process is only for test
cases now do remember that it doesn't
include other objects like test case
templates business test cases modules or
execution lists this is purely for your
test cases
so uh how it is done the test case work
state which you must have seen uh it has
got three uh basically three stages
planned in work and completed and with
this pre-execution approval the test
case work state can be used by Tosca to
change the approval state of the test
cases
so it lets users know how far along the
test cases is either planned in work or
completed
now if we use pre-execution approval
only Tosca can change the state
um automatically so if for every new
test case that's in progress has the
state planned and when a user requests
approval for a test case Tosca changes
it to in work
and then approved test cases get the
state completed and rejected test cases
go back to planned
so this is how the test cases
pre-execution approval works now ideally
um I would have shown you how it works
but it is not possible uh to show you
this feature currently because I'm
working on a single user workspace and
this particular feature works when you
are working within a team on a
multi-user workspace right so that it
goes through different uh review process
before that test cases can be approved
and then go into the execution that
would be a specific User Group assigned
and that user group will take care of
reviewing the test cases and then
approving them okay but I can tell you
that if you're working on a multi-user
workspace you can go to your root
project level and right click and then
you can enable that feature right from
this particular menu okay you can always
create your own user group
at at this level so that that user group
would be taking care of this whole
approval and review process
so uh that's all about this particular
feature it is very interesting uh to
know
um I wish I could have shown you more on
this feature but maybe in the later
sessions I would try to show you this
new feature which is available in Tosca
16.0
so that's all for this session I hope it
was interesting to know all the new
features uh which are currently
available in Tosca 16.0 I would highly
recommend all of you to upgrade to the
latest version of Tosca if you have not
already done or if you are installing it
completely new uh it's a good time to
start installing Tosca 16.0 and
interacting with all the different new
features which are currently available
there are lots of different enhancements
which would help you to increase your
automation coverage and especially if
you're working with Erp applications
then there are lots of different
features which can help your automation
become more robust and also decrease at
the time you spend on customizing your
automation for these applications
so keep watching uh we'll be coming up
with more interesting Tosca lessons